Guide to the William S. Vickrey Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Manuscripts
  - Subseries III.7: Taxation
    - The Corporate Income Tax in the U.S. Tax System, paper, 27 March 1992 (Box 22, Folder 363)
      [For presentation at the Manhattan Institute session, Century Club, 1 April 1992. Discusses leveling the playing field for capital gains, methods of eliminating the baneful effects of the corporate income tax, rationalization of formulas for allocation of income among jurisdictions, and replacing the foreign tax credit with a separation of the income tax into a normal source-based tax and a destination-based surtax.]
    - Cumulative Assessment: Some Responses to Richard Goode's Critique, paper (Box 22, Folder 364)
      [Discusses averaging.]
    - Cumulative Averaging after Thirty Years, paper, 1972 (Box 22, Folder 365)
      [Published in Modern Fiscal Issues: Essays in Honor of Carl S. Shoup. Edited by Richard M. Bird and John G. Head. University of Toronto Press, 1972. Review of some of the possible causes for failure of adoption.]
    - Design of Taxes to Minimize Evasion, paper, Oct. 1977 (Box 22, Folder 366)
      [Paper for conference on "Tax Losses in Turkey and Preventative Measures", Istanbul, 25-27 Oct. 1977. See also Economic and Social Studies Conference Board of Turkey Conference, Box 40, Folder 693.]
    - The Effect of the Tax System on the Impact of Government Debt, paper, 18 Sept. 1990 (Box 22, Folder 367)
    - Estimating Income Tax Revenue under Alternative Rate Structures, paper, 1969 (Box 22, Folder 368)
    - Excise Tax, paper (Box 22, Folder 369)
      [Makes reference to a paper by Vickrey: "Can Excises Lower Prices" Essays in Economics and Econometrics: A Volume in Honor of Harold Hotelling. Edited by Ralph W. Pfouts. Chapel Hill: UNC Press, 1962.]
    - Expenditure, Capital Gains, and the Basis of Progressive Taxation, article, 1968-1969, (langcode="ger">German) (Box 22, Folder 370)
      [German translation reprinted in Finanztheory, Horst Claus Recktenwald, Herausgeber, Köln, Kiepenhauer and Witech, 1969, pp. 425-33. Discusses the capital gains issue.]
    - Improvements Tax in a Monocentric City, notes (Box 22, Folder 371)
    - Income Tax Impasse, article, ca. 1957 (Box 22, Folder 372)
      [Op. Ed. piece for Challenge magazine. ]
    - Justice, Equality, and the Economic System, paper, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 373)
      [Published in Small Comforts for Hard Times. Edited by Michael Mooney and Florian Stuber. New York: Columbia University Press, 1977. Discusses Rawls, Utilitarianism, Pareto efficient redistribution, and redistributive public finance.]
    - A Modern Theory of Land Value Taxation, paper, 1992 (Box 22, Folder 374)
      [Paper for a Session on "New Concepts of Taxation", COPE Conference, Rio de Janeiro, 8-12 January 1992. Discusses the problems in use- and state-neutral assessment.]
    - Note on Taxation in New Hampshire, review, 27 July 1992 (Box 22, Folder 375)
    - Notes and Issues Concerning an Expenditures Tax, paper, Oct. 1978 (Box 22, Folder 376)
      [Paper for Brookings Conference, 19-20 Oct. 1978. Discusses cumulative assessment under a consumption tax, a net worth tax to replace estate and gift taxes, and cumulative averaging under an expenditures tax.]
    - Notes on Proposed California Severance Tax, notes, [1968?] (Box 22, Folder 377)
    - Private Philanthropy and Public Finance, paper, June 1973 (Box 23, Folder 378)
    - Problems in Land Value Taxation: Equity, Expectation, and Efficiency, paper, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 379)
      [Prepared for presentation at the Symposium on the Land Tax in Honor of Professor Harry Gunnison Brown, University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo., 6 April 1973. Discusses the switch from current system to land value taxation, the objection that a sudden shift expropriates legitimately acquired values does not hold when this is the result of shifting from other localized taxes, and that owners of land can gain from increased land taxation.]
    - Progression, Simplification, and a Level Playing Field, paper, 20 Jan. 1995 (Box 23, Folder 380)
    - Reforma de Impuestos sobre Donaciones y Herencias, Tema No. 16, lecture notes, 21 July 1976, (langcode="spa">Spanish) (Box 23, Folder 381)
      [Discusses gift and inheritance taxation.]
    - Reforma del Impuesto Sobre Rentas (ingresos netos), Tema No. 15, lecture notes, 20 July 1976, (langcode="spa">Spanish) (Box 23, Folder 382)
    - Security Equity for Working Wives via Earned Income Credit, paper, Feb. 1968 (Box 23, Folder 383)
    - Simplification, Progression, and a Level Playing Field, paper, 1995-1996 (Box 23, Folder 384)
    - Simplification through Cumulative Averaging, paper, ca. 1969 (Box 23, Folder 385)
    - Some Preliminary Thoughts on Basic Principles of the Taxation of Multinational Activity, paper, [1974?] (Box 23, Folder 386)
    - Special Report on New Tax Frontiers for the National Governors' Conference, paper, 25 June 1968 (Box 23, Folder 387)
    - Statement for Chairman's Summary Report: NGC Revenue and Taxation Committee, 6. New Tax Frontiers, paper (Box 23, Folder 388)
    - Statement regarding Party Planks on Federal Tax Reform, paper, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 389)
      [Prepared for Taxation with Representation, a nonprofit, nonpartisan, public interest tax lobby that deals solely with federal tax issues.]
    - Tax Simplification through Cumulative Averaging, paper, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 390)
      [Published in Law and Contemporary Problems: Tax Simplification and Reform, 34(4), Autumn 1969, 736-50. Argues that cumulative averaging be viewed as a master stroke of simplification, in spite of being reportedly rejected out of hand as too complicated.]
    - Teoria del Progresion, Tema No. 17, lecture notes, 22 July 1976, (langcode="spa">Spanish) (Box 23, Folder 391)
    - An Updated Agenda for Progressive Taxation, paper, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 392)
      [Published in Papers and Proceedings, American Economic Association, March 1992, 257-62. Discusses capital gains, inflation, corporate income tax, undistributed profits tax, transnational incomes, tax-exempt bonds, home ownership, and leisure.]
  - Subseries III.8: Transportation
    Papers, reviews, letters to the editor, essays, statements, outlines, speeches, reports, and notes regarding the numerous economic aspects of transportation. These materials reflect his observations on transit fares, automation, road pricing, parking, land use, toll systems, airline timetables, subway scheduling, transfers, highway use, direct current traction, and methods of examining transportation demand for pricing. Vickrey proposes solutions to the problems with congestion, pollution, subway service, parking allocation, inadequate maps, traffic accidents, financing, signaling, politics, and inefficient use of transportation infrastructure. In addition, some documents address the specific transportation concerns in New York City, Caracas, Buenos Aires, Washington, D.C., Tehran, Korea, and the Netherlands. Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - After the Defeat of the Bond Issue, What?, paper, 17 Oct. 1973 (Box 23, Folder 393)
    - Airline Guide, notes (Box 23, Folder 394)
      [Includes algorithm for itineraries, examples, and other notes.]
    - Alleviating Rush-Hour Crowding: Comment, review, March 1974 (Box 23, Folder 395)
      [Comments on a proposal by Professor Charles Libove in Transportation Engineering Journal, 1973. Discusses overlength trains, skip stop scheduling, and "overlap" scheduling. Includes appendix on "The Effects of various operational modes on volume of service."]
    - Alternative Method of Implementing Subscriber Fares, paper (Box 23, Folder 396)
    - Analysis of Minimum Headways in Rapid Transit Service, paper, Aug. 1971 (Box 23, Folder 397)
      [Makes reference to a computer program for train control.]
    - Appendix II: Suggested Algorithm for Processing a Basic or Local Airport Set, fragment (Box 23, Folder 398)
    - Automatic Control of Subway Service Perturbations, paper, May 1973 (Box 23, Folder 399)
    - Better Subway Safety, letter to the editor, 23 Sept. 1995 (Box 23, Folder 400)
    - Bibliography on the Costs and Pricing of Streets and Highways, list, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 401)
    - Caracas Road Pricing Study, paper, 1970-1973 (Box 23, Folder 402)
    - A Change-Free, Time-Origin-Destination Fare Collection System, paper, 1 May 1966 (Box 24, Folder 403)
    - Charging Users of Transportation Infrastructure, paper, Dec. 1991 (Box 24, Folder 404)
      [Draft of a proposed Congressional Budget Office paper with some marginal comments.]
    - A Check-list of Points to be Considered in Planning Improvements and Economies in Subway Service, paper, June 1953 (Box 24, Folder 405)
    - Comments on the "Tolls Pricing Study of Port Authority of NY and NJ", FWHA Docket 76-9, paper, Jan. 1979 (Box 24, Folder 406)
      [Discusses the implementation of peak-load pricing in New York City anticipating a bottleneck model with heterogeneous users.]
    - Computers, Pricing Mechanisms, and Optimum Traffic and Transit Patterns, paper (Box 24, Folder 407)
    - Congestion in Midtown Manhattan in Relation to Marginal Cost Pricing, paper, May 1991 (Box 24, Folder 408)
      [Argument on the basis of which Vickrey claimed that the marginal cost pricing of a trip in Manhattan on a weekday is $1,000.]
    - Congestion Theory and Transport Investment, paper, 1968-1970 (Box 24, Folder 409)
      [For presentation at a meeting of the American Economic Association, 28 Dec. 1968. Discusses optimal investment, with and without congestion pricing.]
    - Continuous Automatic Bus Spacing and Dispatching (CASBAD): A Proposal for Improving the Efficiency of Short-Headway Bus Service, paper, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 410)
      [The proposal suggests using automatic digitalized radio signals.]
    - Controlling the Environmental Impact of the Automobile, outline, 17 Oct. 1972 (Box 24, Folder 411)
      [Outline of presentation at VPI Conference on the Environment, 17 Oct. 1972.]
    - Converting to Efficient Transit Fares, paper, 17 Aug. 1995 (Box 24, Folder 412)
      [Concerned with the mechanical aspects of phasing-in an efficient fare structure.]
    - Cost Reduction and Efficiency Promotion through Pricing in Urban Transportation, abstract (Box 24, Folder 413)
    - Current Economic Position and Prospects of Argentina: Planning and Public Investment in the Buenos Aires Metropolitan Area, paper, 1970 (Box 24, Folder 414)
      [Confidential report to the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development. Comments on skip stop scheduling, brake wear, coordination between platforms of trains, push-pull service, and express service.]
    - Current Issues in Urban Transportation, paper (1 of 4), 1968-1973 (Box 24, Folder 415)
      [Published in Contemporary Economic Issues. Edited by Neil Chamberlain. Irwin, 1969. A wide-ranging discussion of urban transportation issues.]
    - Current Issues in Urban Transportation, paper (2 of 4), 1968-1973 (Box 25, Folder 416)
    - Current Issues in Urban Transportation, paper (3 of 4), 1968-1973 (Box 25, Folder 417)
    - Current Issues in Urban Transportation, paper (4 of 4), 1968-1973 (Box 25, Folder 418)
    - Dealing with Divergence or Slow Convergence in a Traffic Assignment Problem, paper, April 1972 (Box 25, Folder 419)
    - Denver Transcript, speech (Box 25, Folder 420)
      [Notes hypercongestion as a queuing reservoir.]
    - Detailed Pricing of Urban Transportation Services: The Essential Key to Efficient Urban Transportation, paper, Aug. 1973 (Box 25, Folder 421)
      [Published in Proceedings International Symposium, "Man and Transport", Tokyo, Asahi Shimbun, 3-7 Sept. 1973. Discusses congestion charges and the lack of burden on non-driving poor. See also International Symposium "1973 Man and Transport", Box 41, Folder 701.]
    - The Economic Efficiency of the Present Road User Charges System, and Some Observations on the Value of Time in the Evaluation of Road User Charges, paper, 18 Feb. 1972 (Box 25, Folder 422)
      [Technical Note No. 10, Task No. 23.]
    - The Economics of Intra-Urban Transportation, paper (Box 25, Folder 423)
    - Efficiency through Pricing in Urban Transportation, paper (Box 25, Folder 424)
    - Efficient Allocation of In-House Parking Space, paper, 12 Aug. 1992 (Box 25, Folder 425)
      [Discusses the application of auctions to allocation of parking space within, say, a university.]
    - Efficient Pricing of City Facilities and Services, paper, 2 Dec. 1992 (Box 25, Folder 426)
      [Notes for testimony for NYC Controller's Office, 2 Dec. 1992. Discusses congestion pricing, subway fares and service, utility rates, and site value taxation.]
    - Energy Saving in Direct Current Traction, paper, 1975-1982 (Box 25, Folder 427)
      [Discusses the design of traction engine for buses and includes circuit diagrams and notes. See also Low Loss DC Traction for Rapid Transit Service, Box 26, Folder 445.]
    - Equipment Husbandry, notes (Box 26, Folder 428)
    - Externalities in Public Facility Use: The Case of Highway Accidents, paper, April 1968 (Box 26, Folder 429)
      [Prepared for Conference on the Economics of Public Output, Universities-National Bureau Committee for Economic Research, 26-27 April 1968. Discusses marginal costs in relation to insurance, traffic density, tort law, and administrative costs.]
    - A Flexible, Change-free Fare Collection System for Buses and Subways, paper, 10 May 1966 (Box 26, Folder 430)
    - Further Notes on Fare Collection for the Rationalized Commuter Service, paper, 17 June 1962 (Box 26, Folder 431)
    - Immediate Congestion Relief for E and F Riders, essay, Feb. 1992 (Box 26, Folder 432)
    - Immediate Steps Towards an Efficient Transit Fare Structure, paper (Box 26, Folder 433)
      [Discusses New York City.]
    - Improvement of Broadway IRT Service, essay, March 1966 (Box 26, Folder 434)
    - Improvement of Quick Reference Airline Timetables, notes, April 1982 (Box 26, Folder 435)
      [Superseded presumably by computers.]
    - Increasing Capacity at Transit Bottlenecks, paper, 7 Sept. 1995 (Box 26, Folder 436)
      [Discusses more efficient use of existing subway capacity.]
    - Information Requirements for Meaningful Evaluation of Alternative Solutions to Metropolitan Transportation Problems, paper (Box 26, Folder 437)
    - An Interim Plan for Street Parking Licenses, paper, 7 Dec. 1971 (Box 26, Folder 438)
    - JFK to Penn Station, essay, 18 June 1996 (Box 26, Folder 439)
    - Letter to Dr. William Ronan, Port Authority of NY and NJ, letter, 23 May 1977 (Box 26, Folder 440)
      [Advocates time-varying tolls and peak-load pricing in New York City.]
    - Letter to the New York Times, letter to the editor (Box 26, Folder 441)
      [Discusses tolls.]
    - Letter to the New York Times, letter to the editor, 12 April 1978 (Box 26, Folder 442)
      [Discusses parking meters and cards.]
    - Lexington-Pelham Skip-Stop Scheduling, paper, 1972 (Box 26, Folder 443)
    - Low Loss DC Traction for Rapid Transit Service, notes, 1971 (Box 26, Folder 444)
      [Includes circuit diagrams.]
    - Low Loss DC Traction for Rapid Transit Service, paper, Nov. 1971 (Box 26, Folder 445)
      [See also Energy Saving in Direct Current Traction, Box 25, Folder 427.]
    - Making the Most of Urban Roadways, speech, 26 March 1966 (Box 26, Folder 446)
      [Sketch of remarks for Engineering Dean's Day, Columbia University. Argues that rational use requires collaboration among engineers, economists, and politicians with special attention to efficient pricing of alternatives.]
    - More Revenue and Better Usage from Curb Parking, paper (Box 26, Folder 447)
      [Discusses parking vouchers.]
    - New Systems versus Better Use of Old Systems: Criteria and Cases, paper, 1974 (Box 26, Folder 448)
      [For Econometric Society--Association for the Study of Grants Economy, San Francisco, 29 Dec. 1974. Covers a litany of inefficiencies: monumentalism and other biases in favor of large-scale capital outlays; over-generous pensions and other forms of political time-bomb planting; transit service with small cross-section, shorter station platforms, low train weight per unit length, and high frequency under continuous control and skip-stop scheduling through bottlenecks; fares simulating futures markets for car ferries and airline seats; schedule coordination; and transit fares on a marginal social cost basis.]
    - New York Needs an Efficient Fare Structure, letter to editor, 25 Aug. 1995 (Box 26, Folder 449)
    - Notes Concerning the Caracas Metro, paper, Aug. 1971 (Box 27, Folder 450)
    - Notes for Public Transit Finance Workshop, notes, 14 Sept. 1976 (Box 27, Folder 451)
    - Notes on an Interim Fare Structure for Suburban Service, notes, 1 May 1962 (Box 27, Folder 452)
    - Notes on Cambridge Road Pricing Proposals, notes, Nov. 1991 (Box 27, Folder 453)
    - Notes on "Charging Users of Transportation Infrastructure", review, 27 Dec. 1991 (Box 27, Folder 454)
      [Possibly notes for discussion of a paper at an AEA meeting.]
    - Notes on Cromwell: Financing NY Subways, review (Box 27, Folder 455)
    - Notes on Jim O'Shea memo "Time to Review Transit Options", notes (Box 27, Folder 456)
      [Discusses New York City transit.]
    - Notes on Land, Traffic, and Markets, notes, 15 Oct. 1991 (Box 27, Folder 457)
      [For presentation at Henry George Breakfast, University Club, 15 Oct. 1991.]
    - Notes on Subway Finance, notes, 22 Dec. 1971 (Box 27, Folder 458)
      [Various recommendations for sources and uses of funds in New York City.]
    - Notes on The Abstract Mode Model by Quant and Baumol, book review, Sept. 1966 (Box 27, Folder 459)
    - Notes on the Analysis of Transportation Demand, notes, Aug. 1973 (Box 27, Folder 460)
    - Notes on "The Economic Analysis of Rural Road Projects, World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 241" by C. Carnemark, Jamie Biderman, and David Bovet, review, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 461)
    - Notes on the Further Development of the Netherlands Transit Subsidy Project, fragments, 8 Aug. 1980 (Box 27, Folder 462)
      [Discusses optimal transit subsides. ]
    - Notes on the Law and Economics of Highway Use, notes, March 1977 (Box 27, Folder 463)
    - Notes on the New Subway Map, notes, Feb. 1978 (Box 27, Folder 464)
      [Discusses New York City subway map.]
    - Notes on Transit Fare Structure and Finance, notes, 10 July 1993 (Box 27, Folder 465)
    - Notes on Urban Transportation Issues, notes, Jan. 1971 (Box 27, Folder 466)
      [Thorough set of notes with a discussion of hypercongestion and comments on shadow value of urban land and transit service.]
    - Observations on Modern Transit, paper, 23 Dec. 1985 (Box 27, Folder 467)
      [Version 6. Part of Discussion Paper Series, Columbia University, Aug. 1987. Discusses fares, fare systems, subsidies, economic infrastructure design, cost-benefit analysis of operating methods, automatic control and signaling for higher frequencies and regularity, energy saving traction.]
    - On Assigning a Value to Changes in Service Frequency, paper, Aug. 1962 (Box 27, Folder 468)
    - Optimization of Traffic and Facilities, paper, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 469)
      [Published in Journal of Transport Economics and Policy, 1(2), Jan. 1967, 123-36. Discusses marginal cost pricing for control of congestion and optimal timing of construction.]
    - Outline of Registration Apparatus for Reusable Subscriber Card Systems, outline (Box 27, Folder 470)
    - Overall Outline of Processing Procedure for Full Itinerary Development, outline (Box 27, Folder 471)
      [Includes design of an algorithm.]
    - Politics versus Efficiency in Transit Fares, letter to editor, 25 June 1966 (Box 27, Folder 472)
    - Possible Topics for Study in Urban Transportation, notes, 4 Dec. 1968 (Box 27, Folder 473)
      [Includes a list of research topics.]
    - A Preliminary Sketch of Possible Schemes for Automatic Toll Assessment with Reference to the Washington, D.C. Metropolitan Area, paper (Box 27, Folder 474)
    - Prices and Rates in Korean Transportation, preliminary draft, Aug. 1972 (Box 28, Folder 475)
      [For Princeton Contract AID/csd-159.]
    - Prices and Rates in Korean Transportation, report, 1972 (Box 28, Folder 476)
    - Prices and Rates in Korean Transportation, research materials, 1969-1972 (Box 28, Folder 477)
    - Pricing as a Tool in Coordination of Land Transportation, paper, April 1963 (Box 28, Folder 478)
      [For Conference on Transport Economics, National Bureau of Economic Research, 26-27 April 1963.]
    - Pricing in the Planning of Transportation Facilities, paper, 15 Jan. 1979 (Box 28, Folder 479)
      [For presentation at the meetings of the Transportation Research Board, Shoreham Americana, 15 Jan. 1979.]
    - Pricing in Urban and Suburban Transport, paper, 1962-1963 (Box 28, Folder 480)
      [Published in American Economic Review, 52(2), May 1963, 452-65. Discusses a litany of inefficiencies related to departures of prices from short-run marginal social cost.]
    - Pricing of Urban Transportation: Economic Desiderata, Technology Possibility, and Political Constraints, outline, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 481)
      [Outline of paper for ICT Conference, Denver, 1973.]
    - Pricing Transport Services, essay, 5 Aug. 1980 (Box 28, Folder 482)
    - Principles and Applications of Congestion Pricing, paper, 1993 (Box 28, Folder 483)
      [Overview and new material using intersection queuing theory to compute tolls at intersections and optimal signaling.]
    - Principles of Efficient Congestion Pricing, paper, 1991 (Box 28, Folder 484)
    - Priorities for the City, 1973, paper, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 485)
      [Discusses engineering aspects of subways, skip stop scheduling, and other methods of improving subway service.]
    - Privatization and Marketization of Transport, paper, 1993 (Box 29, Folder 486)
    - Promoting Efficient Use of On-Street Parking, paper, 11 Aug. 1995 (Box 29, Folder 487)
    - A Proposal for Increased Service on the IND Queens and Central Park West Express Lines, essay, March 1966 (Box 29, Folder 488)
    - Queries Regarding Taxi Services, notes (Box 29, Folder 489)
    - Queuing Models, notes (Box 29, Folder 490)
      [Very sketchy.]
    - The Relief of Congestion on the 8th Ave. Line, essay, 5 March 1966 (Box 29, Folder 491)
    - Report on Mission to Teheran, Iran: Notes on Transport Planning, Electricity and Telephone Rates for Teheran, report, April 1975 (Box 29, Folder 492)
      [Prepared for United Nations. ]
    - Resistance to Rational Decision-Making in Transportation: Pricing and Marketing Practices and Consequences, outline, 7 May 1969 (Box 29, Folder 493)
      [Outline of discussion to be presented at the National Seminar on Urban Transportation for Tomorrow, Denver, 7 May 1969.]
    - Returns to Scale in Transit: A Comment, review, March 1977 (Box 29, Folder 494)
      [Comments on the various methodological and definitional difficulties with the analysis by Paul McDevitt in The Logistics and Transportation Review, 1976, pp. 233-49.]
    - Review of Transportation Economics by Herbert Mohring, review, Jan. 1977 (Box 29, Folder 495)
      [Transportation Economics by Herbert Mohring, Cambridge, Mass.: Ballinger Publishing Company, 1976.]
    - Revising New York's Subway Fare Structure, paper, 1955 (Box 29, Folder 496)
      [A revised and condensed version of the Mayor's Committee monograph later published in Operations Research for Management. Vol. III. Edited by Joseph F. McClosky and John Coppinger. John Hopkins, 1956.]
    - Revising the Taxi Fare Structure, paper, ca. 1974 (Box 29, Folder 497)
    - Road Pricing: Key to Efficient Urban Transport, paper (Box 29, Folder 498)
      [Discusses congestion pricing. ]